# YASWANT DEVARAKONDA

Texas A&M University, Department of Physics & Astronomy | \$\subseteq 832-766-8531 | \$\subseteq\$ yaswantd@tamu.edu | \$\subseteq tx.ag/yaswantd

### RESEARCH INTERESTS

Type Ia Supernova - Ultraviolet Emission - Super-Chandrasekhar Mass Supernova - CSM Interaction Binary Companion Interaction - Supernova/Host Galaxy Relations - Cosmology - Astrostatistics

# **BACKGROUND**

#### **Texas A&M University**

PhD in Astronomy Expected: May 2023 M.S. in Astronomy December 2021 **Applied Statistics Certificate** December 2021

Associate Certificate from the Center for the Integration of Research, Teaching, and Learning

July 2019

#### The University of Texas at Austin

B.S. in Physics, B.S. in Astronomy

May 2018

#### **SKILLS**

Proficient: Python, Excel, PowerPoint, Word, UNIX, and LaTex.

Familiar: GIT, HTML, JMP, R

# RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

### Graduate Research Assistant, Texas A&M University

Fall 2020 - Current

Advisors: Dr. Peter Brown & Dr. Nicholas Suntzeff

- Creating the first UV/optical Hubble diagram that uses Type Ia SNe in the Hubble flow using Swift UVOT and HST observations
- Developed a template fitting routine to estimate UV/optical dust extinction and k-corrections for SNe Ia
- Compared the UV and optical properties of SNe Ia light curves to provide statistical constraints on diversity and correlation across wavelength regimes

## Graduate Research Assistant, Texas A&M University

Fall 2018 - Summer 20200

Advisor: Dr. Jonelle Walsh

- Analyzed connections between SMBHs and their host galaxies for the MASSIVE survey
- Estimated contributions to the total mass of galaxies based on their stellar and dark matter components
- Created kinematic maps of galaxies based on IFU spectroscopy of their stellar populations

# Undergraduate Research Assistant, University of Texas at Austin

Fall 2015 - Summer 2018

Advisor: Dr. Steve Finkelstein

- Examined gravitationally lensed Lyman-Alpha emmitting galaxies to fill out the faint end of the LAE luminosity function
- Led a team of 5 students in calibrating IFU spectrographs as part of the HETDEX project
- Measured the PSF of DECam data as part of the HETDEX survey

### **TEACHING EXPERIENCE**

# Instructor of Record

ASTR 102: Observational Astronomy, Texas A&M University

Fall 2019 - Spring 2021

- Taught a total of 160 students observing and research techniques useful in modern astronomy
- Developed new lesson plans and lab activities for students learning in virtual or hybrid formats in response to the COVID-19 pandemic
- Implemented evidence-based teaching techniques to sustain student participation during virtual and hybrid learning

### **Teaching Assistant**

ASTR 111: Overview of Modern Astronomy (Lab), Texas A&M University

Fall 2018 - Spring 2019

- Led a total of 80 students in an activity based exploration of astronomical concepts

• AST 321: The Future of Humanity, University of Texas at Austin

Spring 2018

- Graded assignments for 60 students in an essay based course that combined concepts from astronomy, engineering, anthropology, and philosophy
- AST 309: The Lives and Deaths of Stars, University of Texas at Austin

Fall 2017

- Graded assignments for 80 students
- AST 301: Introduction to Astronomy, University of Texas at Austin

Fall 2016 - Spring 2017

- Provided assistance in class and through office hours and proctored exams for a total of 240 students

#### **SERVICE**

• AggieNova Undergraduate Research Group Summer 2022 - Current - Mentoring a team of 4 undergraduate students in individual research projects Fall 2019 - Current Mentoring and Advising Graduates in an Inclusive Community (MAGIC) Mentoring first-year PhD students with regular meetings and professional development workshops Texas A&M University Graduate and Professional Student Government (GPSG) - Advocacy Committee Co-Chair for Legislative Affairs Summer 2022 - Current - Senator Fall 2020 - Current - Wrote and Introduced GPSG Bill 55.07: On the Accessibility of Menstrual Health Products on Campus • Texas A&M Queer Empowerment Council - Co-Founder, Treasurer Fall 2022-Current Assembled leaders of LGBTQ+ related organizations to directly advocate for queer students, faculty, and staff with the university administration and local and state governments. • American Astronomical Society Congressional Visits Day - Selected Participant, Legislative Branch 2-4 May 2022 - Selected Participant, Executive Branch 20 July 2022 - AAS Policy Blog Guest Post 8 August 2022 Graduates Learning Astronomy Skills Seminar (GLASS) Fall 2020 - Summer 2022 - Co-Chair, host and develop professional development workshops for graduate students and postdocs Society for the Underrepresented in Physics and Astronomy (SUPA) Fall 2020 - Summer 2022 Co-Chaired organization focused on highlighting DEI issues within the department and providing community support for marginalized people • Discover, Explore, and Enjoy Phyics and Engineering (DEEP) Fall 2020 - Spring 2022 - Mentored a total of 7 undergraduates in creating demonstrations aimed at K-12 students • Conference for Undergraduate Women in Physics (CUWiP), Texas A&M University 17-19 January 2020 - Organizing Committee, Panel Moderator, Social Media Co-Lead • Astronomy Students Association, University of Texas at Austin Fall 2014 - Spring 2018 President Fall 2016 - Summer 2017 Secretary Fall 2015 - Summer 2016 • Undergraduate Astrophysical Journal Club, University of Texas at Austin Summer 2017 - Summer 2018 - Founder, Co-Chair **OUTREACH**  Astronomy on Tap BCS Fall 2018 - Current - What's Up Segment Host - Show Host (recurring) - Presenter (recurring) • Texas A&M Physics and Engineering Festival (Physics Fest) Spring 2019 - Current - Astronomy Demonstrations Co-Lead Spring 2021-Spring 2022 - Organized teams of undergraduate and graduate students to present demonstrations at a festival attended by 5,000 K-12 students Astronomy on Tap ATX Spring 2017 - Summer 2018 Stargazing Coordinator Painter Hall Observatory Spring 2017 - Summer 2018 - Telescope Operator and Star Party Host TALKS & PRESENTATIONS • Science Seminar Series, University of Wisconsin-Madison - Invited Talk: Unlocking the Ultraviolet Properties of Type Ia Supernovae 17 October 2022 • Time Domain and Multi-Messenger Astrophysics NASA Workshop, Annapolis, Maryland - Poster: Type Ia Supernovae in the UV and Optical 22-24 August 2022 • 240th Meeting of the American Astronomical Society, Pasadena, California iPoster: Early Light-Curves of Type Ia Supernovae in the Ultraviolet 13 June 2022 • Cook's Branch Supernova Retreat, Montgomery, TX Talk: Early Light Curves of Type Ia SNe in the UV and Optical 15 March 2022 • ComSciCon Houston, Rice University - Talk: Type Ia SNe in the Ultraviolet 5 March 2022 • SuperVirtual 2021 (Virtual) - Poster: Comparing Type Ia Supernovae in the Ultraviolet and Optical 17 November 2021 • Statistical Challanges in Modern Astronomy VII (Virtual) - Virtual Poster: The Variability of Type Ia Supernovae in the Ultraviolet 7 June 2021 • Frank N. Bash Symposium, University of Texas at Austin

22 October 2019

23 October 2017

- Poster: Using Stellar Kinematics to Measure Black Hole Masses

- Poster: The Faint End of the Lyman Alpha Luminosity Function from  $2 \le z \le 3.8$ 

- 231st Meeting of the American Astronomical Society, Washington, DC
  - Poster: The Faint End of the Lyman Alpha Luminosity Function from 2 $\leq z \leq$  3.8

9 January 2018

- Texas Undergraduate Research Symposium, Rice University
  - Talk: The Faint End of the Lyman Alpha Luminosity Function from  $2 \le z \le 3.8$

13 October 2017

# **PUBLICATIONS**

### **First Author**

Comparisons of Type Ia Supernova Light Curves in the UV and Optical with the Swift Ultra-violet/Optical Telescope Y. Devarakonda & P. J. Brown, The Astronomical Journal, Volume 163, Issue 6, id.258, 10 pp. (2022) ADS

#### Co-Author

The Spitzer-HETDEX Exploratory Large Area Survey. II. The Dark Energy Camera and Spitzer/IRAC Multiwavelength Catalog I. G. B. Wold, L. Kawinwanichakij, M. L. Stevens, S. L. Finkelstein, C. Papovich, Y. Devarakonda, and 12 additional authors The Astrophysical Journal Supplement Series, Volume 240, Issue 1, article id. 5, 21 pp. (2019) ADS

# **Contributing Author**

The Hobby-Eberly Telescope Dark Energy Experiment (HETDEX) Survey Design, Reductions, and Detections K. Gebhardt, E. Mentuch Cooper, R. Ciardullo, V, and 60 additional authors including **Y. Devarakonda** The Astrophysical Journal, Volume 923, Issue 2, id.217, 39 pp. (2021) ADS